Well, I would begin with Darfur,
the annihilation
of populations
just because they have another religion
or are of another race.
And the world is not interested in them
because they
have no resources.
No oil…
Problems.
If you squeeze a newspaper,
it seems like it will bleed.
We are just born.
We're just born somewhere on planet Earth
and if we don’t want to stay there
we go somewhere else.
But then, when we go somewhere else,
we're discriminated against.
I arrived two days ago
and on the 11th I must leave again
because my visa lasts for only four days.
As a Colombian,
as a citizen of the world,
I have no right to enter this paradise,
the paradise of the First World,
except for four days.
The day that the law
has effectively realized the possibility
of granting this right without restriction to all people,
on that day humanity will have done more
than pass over a boundary.
It will have attained a degree of evolution
fully to be desired by all cultures and nations.
Everyone can gain human dignity for themselves.
Before this, though, one must leave behind
the self-imposed oppression
of politics, ideology, religion
and nationalistic narrow-mindedness.
I come…
I come from the jungle
where I lived for the most part of my life with tribes
and where
the question of freedom
is much more meaningful than it is here.
I have never known more free beings than them,
the indigenous people…
no, I never have.
I knew it
from the moment that this murmur first began,
and this babble.
It sent a shiver down my spine
and I realized that something will come of this,
that it's helping.
I was reminded a little of 'Wings of Desire'…
There are these angels hearing all these voices.
There's this similar kind of murmur the whole time.
And then this murmur was here, only it was real.
All these people really were thinking aloud.
This question is a bit racist.
If all Chinese people want to have a car,
presuming that they would want to drive
the most powerful, the biggest and the fastest cars,
then the skies above us would darken.
What if all Chinese people want a car?
Then all German people
must be turned into automobile workers
to produce cars for the Chinese
until all the Germans are exhausted.
It's an impossible story.
The problem is not how many people want a car
but that the door to human desires
has been opened interminably.
How can we close the door again
after opening it to our infinite, possessive desires?
I'm speaking…
I'm speaking so much
about all the problems.
I'm setting it all on fire!
There are enough coffee pots in the world.
There are enough gadgets surrounding us.
There are enough chairs!
Use one of the many hundreds that are already there
and then put your energy into developing
those things that really matter.
All this forms part of a culture of prostitution.
Our values have become prostituted
and humanity itself just a big prostitution machine.
It's a model
that is destroying us.
It's a model that is consuming us.
The expression 'Third World' is truly an arrogant claim.
It is not a Third World but it is also a world
that has developed in a different way
or that has stood back from development.
But it is not the Third World.
What then would the First World be?
They started first by taking the gold away!
But gold for indigenous people didn’t have the same value
as it did for capitalists.
Oh plundered Africa…
Africa… terrible Africa.
It's impossible to talk about Africa without feeling…
without feeling our hearts twinge.
We also have to understand
that all of the resources
are shared by all
and they are first of all for those in need.
Real property is property by need.
It comes about through need.
When I need a glass of water, then it is mine
by right of need.
Slavery was about the exploitation of raw materials.
Today it's about oil.
Today it's about diamonds.
Today it's about
all the minerals and primary resources.
The countries…
the Latin American countries
continue to suffer exploitation,
the exploitation of their resources.
Just like vampires.
They are vampires!
They use the energy,
the strength and the lives of others
for their own economic prosperity.
'We are children of a world
that has enough for everyone.
But so many remain hungry
while so few are well fed.
One will eat, the other suffer.
This is how it's always been.
Other nations must be poor
so that rich ones can be rich.'
Let me give you an example.
In Iraq now
my country Iraq,
most people cling to
and trust
only their own people
or their neighbors or others from their city.
Before, we did not ask who a person was,
where they came from,
from which city,
from which tribe or family.
We would be friendly, that's all.
I believe that within each of us
there is a racist dictator.
I’m convinced of this.
Because to us the family is closer
than the clan,
the clan is closer than the tribe,
the tribe is closer than the nation,
the nation is closer than humanity.
It is incomprehensible how, day after day,
the world powers can spend so much money
on death.
The most important step
that all the women of the world can take
is not to give their children away
to be turned into soldiers,
to be turned into killers.
I come from a region
where we all started to hate each other
and to kill each other savagely
as if the others were no longer human.
This question
is extremely, extremely, extremely, extremely
extremely close to my heart as an Israeli.
I can only say that, the way I see it,
there's no peace in the Middle East
because of the vanity of Israel.
The only peace now
is false peace,
peace based upon lack of trust.
Well, I believe the main reason is
because of fanatics on both sides.
On both sides.
You can't ignore the fact
that we are deeply scarred as a people,
but instead of trying to heal ourselves
by recognizing that we simply must use compassion,
love and forgiveness,
and engage in dialogue eye to eye,
we keep hiding behind our so-called righteousness
but there is no such thing.
And we feel like we're allowed to do anything
because of what was done to us.
At this very moment, you can see around me
a circle that represents a global community
where, clearly, there is diversity.
diversity of thought,
diversity of ideas,
diversity of concepts.
Is anyone there listening to us?
At some other time?
It might be catapulted into the world
like a discus.
Super.
Yes? Sounds good? That's it? Beautiful
Beautiful.
Our friend the camera.
Solitude is courage.
Hermetics.
Total neutrality.
To be
unsure of yourself
is courage.
You don't know that Chinese prison labor camps
are similar to Soviet gulags
or German concentration camps.
About 40 or 50 million people
have lost their lives there.
I was there for 19 years
before I made it to America.
I didn’t want to talk about this
but finally I have
because we have only one lifetime.
What would Argentina have been without the courage
of the Mothers of the Plaza de Mayo,
who stood up to the dictatorships and terrorism
of the Generals Videla, Massera and Agosti
who 'disappeared' thousands of people
by throwing them into the sea.
What would have become of us
without the lesson in courage
taught by these mothers
who stood before the Casa de Gobierno
every Thursday
with the portraits of their disappeared sons?
Courage means to understand
that these powers are not invincible,
as is being demonstrated by people in the world
who, with courage and indignation,
have managed to expel
transnationals from their countries,
have managed to overthrow and topple governments.
We should keep this in mind and it should make us
all the more radical and motivated
as we don't risk our lives,
but just a little boredom sometimes,
a little ostracism,
a little of our well-being.
Quite simply,
future generations will not be able to understand
our delirium of destruction.
There won't be any state of emergency.
We have been for thousands of years
in a state of emergency.
We delude ourselves into thinking that
these problems are the creation of
our nation, government, religion or race,
but this is not so.
The problem lies within
each individual's consciousness.
It is by our own free choice,
by our own personal efforts,
that we will achieve balance with nature
and so become like all of nature.
Then we will feel
the eternity, perfection and harmony
that is everywhere in nature
except within our own.
Which God?
Which religion?
God is a way of defining
certain archetypes,
certain expectations and
objectives.
God doesn't exist.
I am of Love.
I am of the Universe.
I am God in Action.
There is no God.
God is a symbol
for something that we can't express in words
and that's also why there's no God's religion.
God, we have to imagine, is something
that is not only unknown to us
but is also beyond our knowledge,
that has no quality of being known.
It's like when we ask the question,
what is the color of a circle?
Is it red, green or blue?
No, it's neither blue nor red nor green.
It is also not colorless.
The question about the color of the circle is absurd
because a circle knows no color.
Many people are unwilling to see this.
They take a pen out of their pocket,
draw a circle on a piece of paper
and say, 'Look, this circle is blue.'
Yes, the circle drawn by them is blue
but the color comes from a pen
and not from the circle.
The color of the pen is the religion
with which we express the divinity,
but we cannot draw the circle ourselves.
It is something that has nothing to do with colors
and there are as many religions
as there are colors with which I can draw a circle.
I didn't think we'd make it!
I believe
in a measure of humility
and in a measure of humanity
and in an avowal of beauty
as an antidote to all the brutality
and cruelty of the world.
I believe
that the sacred lives in nature,
not only in the supernatural
but also in the beauty of nature.
I believe
that human beings are metaphysical animals
and always will be because of their mortality.
The human is the only animal that knows it must die.
This is the source of the mystery,
of the unending mystery of human existence.